Tamara Pico

1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1	1100		
CONTACT INFORMATION	tpico@caltech.edu	Division of Geological & Planetary Sciences Arms 256	
	website: tamarapico.com	1200 E. California Blvd. Pasadena, CA, 91125 USA	
Interests	My research centers on using solid Earth deformation as a lens to understand coupling between ice sheets, sea level, and landscapes in the past. In particular I use glacial isostatic adjustment modeling as a tool to infer variations in past ice sheets, as well as to understand how landscapes record solid Earth deformation over the ice age.		
EDUCATION	Harvard University, Cambridge, MA		
	Ph.D in Earth and Planetary Sciences Secondary field in Studies of Women, Gender, and	May 2019 d Sexuality	
	A.M., Earth and Planetary Sciences Mag		
	"Insights from past sea level and landscapes through the lens of solid Earth ice-sheet interactions"		
	Advisor: Jerry X. Mitrovica		
	Princeton University, Princeton, NJ Ju		
	A.B., Chemistry. With certificates in: Material Science & Engineering, Engineering Biology, French Language & Culture		
APPOINTMENTS	Assistant Professor University of California, Santa Cruz	July 2021-	
	NSF EAR Postdoctoral Fellow Caltech - Geological & Planetary Sciences Secondary appointment: Oregon State University 2019 -2021		
	University of California President's Postdo University of California, Santa Cruz	ostdoctoral Fellow 2020-2021	
	Princeton University - Geosciences Field assistant	June 2014 - July 2014	
	Princeton University - Complex Fluids Gro Senior Thesis advised by Prof. Howard A. Stone	August 2013 - April 2014	
Honors and Awards	University of California President's Postdoctoral		
	NSF Earth Sciences Postdoctoral Research Fellow Caltech AGEP Scholar (California Alliance)	$v_{ m Ship} = 2019 - 2021 \ 2019 - 2020 \ $	
	Harvard Bok Center Certificate of Distinction in	~	
	Harvard Bok Center Certificate of Distinction in Harvard Graduate Prize Fellowship	Teaching Award 2018 2018-2019	
	AGU Outstanding Student Paper Award	2013-2013	
	NSE Graduata Research Followship	2015 2018	

NSF Graduate Research Fellowship

Sigma Xi

2014

2015-2018

Publications & Patents

- **Pico, T.**, McGee, D., Mitrovica, J.X., Russell, J., 'Recent constraints on MIS 3 sea level support role of shelf exposure as a control on Indo-Pacific hydroclimate', AGU Paleoceanography & Paleoclimate, 2020.
- **Pico, T.**, Mitrovica, J.X., Mix, A.C., 'Sea-level fingerprinting of the Bering Strait flooding history detects the source of the Younger Dryas climate event', Science Advances, 2020. (highlighted in Harvard Gazette)
- **Pico, T.**, Robel, A., Powell, E., Mix, A., Mitrovica, J., Leveraging the rapid retreat of Amundsen Ice Stream 13,000 yrs ago to reveal insight into North American deglaciation, Geophysical Research Letters, 2019. doi: 10.1029/2019GL084789
- **Pico, T.**, 'Towards an assessment of the impact of sediment loading on Last Interglacial sea-level markers', Geophysical Journal International, 2019. doi: 10.1093/gji/ggz447
- **Pico, T.**, J.X. Mitrovica, Perron, J.T., Ferrier, K.L., Braun, J., 'Influence of glacial isostatic adjustment on river evolution along the U.S. mid-Atlantic coast', Earth & Planetary Science Letters, 2019
- Coulson, S., **Pico**, **T.**, Austermann, J., Moucha R., Mitrovica, J.X., 'The Role of Isostatic Adjustment and Gravitational Effects on the Dynamics of the Messinian Salinity Crisis', Earth & Planetary Science Letters, 2019
- Dalton, A. S., Finkelstein, S. A., Forman, S. L., Barnett, P. J., **Pico, T.** and Mitrovica, J. X. (2019) 'Was the Laurentide Ice Sheet significantly reduced during Marine Isotope Stage 3?', Geology, 47(2), pp. 111–114.
- **Pico, T.**, Birch, L., Weisenberg, J. and Mitrovica, J. X. (2018) 'Refining the Laurentide Ice Sheet at Marine Isotope Stage 3: A data-based approach combining glacial isostatic simulations with a dynamic ice model', Quaternary Science Reviews. 195, pp. 171–179. doi: 10.1016/j.quascirev.2018.07.023.
- Carlson, A. E., Tarasov, L. and **Pico, T.** (2018) 'Rapid Laurentide ice-sheet advance towards southern last glacial maximum limit during marine isotope stage 3', Quaternary Science Reviews. 196, pp. 118–123. doi: 10.1016/j.quascirev.2018.07.039.
- **Pico, T.**, Mitrovica, J. X., Braun, J. and Ferrier, K. L. (2018) 'Glacial isostatic adjustment deflects the path of the ancestral Hudson River', Geology, (7), pp. 1–4. doi: 10.1130/G40221.1 (highlighted in Harvard Gazette)
- Ferrier, K. L., Li, Q., **Pico**, **T.** and Austermann, J. (2018) 'The Influence of Water Storage in Marine Sediment on Sea-Level Change', Geophysical Research Letters, 45(5). doi: 10.1002/2017GL076592.
- **Pico, T.**, Creveling, J. R. and Mitrovica, J. X. (2017) 'Sea-level records from the U.S. mid-Atlantic constrain Laurentide Ice Sheet extent during Marine Isotope Stage 3', Nature Communications. Nature Publishing Group, 8(May), p. 15612. doi: 10.1038/ncomms15612.
- Ferrier, K. L., Austermann, J., Mitrovica, J. X. and **Pico**, **T.** (2017) 'Incorporating sediment compaction into a gravitationally self-consistent model for ice age sea-level change', Geophysical Journal International, 2010, pp. 663–672. doi: 10.1093/gji/ggx293.
- Creveling, J. R., Mitrovica, J. X., Clark, P. U., Waelbroeck, C. and **Pico, T.** (2017) 'Predicted bounds on peak global mean sea level during marine isotope stages 5a and 5c', Quaternary Science Reviews. Elsevier Ltd, 163, pp. 193–208. doi: 10.1016/j.quascirev.2017.03.003.

Pico, T., Mitrovica, J. X., Ferrier, K. L. and Braun, J. (2016) 'Global ice volume during MIS 3 inferred from a sea-level analysis of sedimentary core records in the Yellow River Delta', Quaternary Science Reviews. Elsevier Ltd, 152, pp. 72–79. doi: 10.1016/j.quascirev.2016.09.012.

(Patent) Stone, H.A., Nunes, J., Um, E., Pico, T.: "Novel Droplet-Embedded Microfibers, and Methods and Devices for Preparing and Using Same" U.S. Patent Application No. 14/680,710, filed 2015.

Um, E., Nunes, J. K., Pico, T. and Stone, H. A. (2014) 'Multicompartment microfibers: Fabrication and selective dissolution of composite droplet-in-fiber structures', Journal of Materials Chemistry B, 2(45). doi: 10.1039/c4tb01666a.

SOCIAL STUDIES OF GEOSCIENCE

Pico, T., Bierman, P., Richardson, S., Doyle, K. 'First Authorship Gap in the Geosciences', (in press, AGU Earth & Space Science) Preprint here!

Pico., T., 'The Darker Side of John Wesley Powell', Scientific American, 2019

INVITED SEMINARS UC Berkeley, Colloquium, October 2020

Caltech, GeoClub Seminar, June 2020

Scripps, Polar Seminar, May 2020

Lehigh University, Departmental Series, April 2020

WHOI, Paleo Seminar, April 2020

Northwestern University, February 2020

Cornell University, January 2020

Scripps, IGPP Seminar, January 2020

Jet Propulsion Laboratory, Ice and Ocean Seminar, November 2019

UC Santa Barbara, Earth Science Departmental Seminar, October 2019

Brown University, Lunchtime Seminar, August 2019

Caltech, Special Seminar, April 2019

University of Texas, Austin, DeFord Lecture, March 2019

MIT, COG3 Seminar, February 2019

University of Chicago, Geophysical Sciences Seminar, January 2019

UMass Amherst Quaternary Seminar, November 2018

Lamont-Doherty Columbia University BPE Seminar, October 2018

Princeton University, Brown Bag Solid Earth Seminar, April 2018

University of Vermont, Geology Seminar, April 2018

UC Santa Cruz, Whole Earth Special Seminar, March 2018

GFZ Deutsches GeoForschungZentrum, Earth System Modeling Seminar, May 2017

ETH Zurich, Earth Surface Dynamics Seminar, May 2017

Rutgers University, Special Seminar, March 2017

Oregon State University, Paleoclimate Seminar, September 2016.

CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS AND TALKS

Pico, T., Robel, A., Powell, E., Mix, A., Mitrovica, J., 'Leveraging the rapid retreat of the Amundsen Ice Stream 13,000 yrs ago to constrain large-scale North American deglaciation', AGU Fall Meeting 2019.

Pico, T., J.X. Mitrovica, D. McGee, J.M., Russell, 'An ice-age lever for hydroclimate? Recent constraints on MIS 3 sea level support shelf exposure as major control on Indo-Pacific Warm Pool over the last ice age', AGU Fall Meeting 2019.

Pico, T., 'Body metaphors in field geology: implications for gender- or sex- based harassment', AGU Fall Meeting 2019. (highlighted in EOS)

Pico, T. '150 years later: Revisiting the legacy of John Wesley Powell and his expedition to the Grand Canyon', GSA Fall Meeting 2019. Poster.

T. Pico, L. Birch, J.X.. Mitrovica: "A small Laurentide Ice Sheet until mid-MIS 3: Insights from glacial isostatic adjustment modeling, non-glacial deposits, and sea-level histories", INQUA 2019. Talk.

T. Pico, J.X. Mitrovica, A.C. Mix: "Two-phase flooding of the Bering Strait reflects the sea-level fingerprint of an expanding ice-free corridor", AGU Fall Meeting 2018, Talk.

T. Pico, J.X. Mitrovica, J.T. Perron, K.L. Ferrier, J. Braun: "Ancient landscapes along the U.S. mid-Atlantic coast record glacial isostatic adjustment", AGU Fall Meeting 2017, Talk (Invited).

T. Pico, S. Richardson, P. Bierman, "The first-authorship geoscience gender gap: Underrepresentation of women first authors in leading geoscience journals, 2013-2018", AGU Fall Meeting 2018, Poster.

T. Pico, P. Bierman, J.X. Mitrovica, J.T. Perron, K.L. Ferrier, J. Braun: "The response of U.S. east coast rivers to glacial isostatic adjustment", GSA Fall Meeting 2018, Talk.

T. Pico, J.X. Mitrovica, A.C. Mix: "Linking the timing of the Cordilleran-Laurentide ice saddle retreat to the inundation history of the Bering Strait", Ocean Sciences Meeting 2018, Talk.

T. Pico, J.X. Mitrovica, J.T. Perron, K.L. Ferrier, J. Braun: "Using ancient landscapes along the U.S. mid-Atlantic to assess the influence of glacial isostatic adjustment on river evolution: the case for the Hudson, Delaware, Susquehanna, and Potomac", AGU Fall Meeting 2017, Talk.

T. Pico, J.X. Mitrovica, A.C. Mix: "Reconciling Observations of the Bering Strait Resubmergence with North American Ice Sheet Melt Histories", PALSEA2 2017, Talk.

T. Pico, J.X. Mitrovica, J. Braun, K.L. Ferrier: "Coupling landscapes to solid-Earth deformation

over the ice-age", AGU Fall Meeting 2016, Talk.

- **T. Pico**, J. Mitrovica, J. Creveling: "Inferring global ice volumes during Marine Isotope Stage 3", PALSEA2 2016, Poster presentation.
- **T. Pico**, J. Mitrovica, K. Ferrier, J. Braun: "Using GIA and sediments to reconstruct past sea level and investigate landscape evolution", CIFAR Meeting 2016, Talk.
- **T. Pico**, J. Mitrovica, K. Ferrier, J. Braun: "Sediments, Sea level, and Global Ice Volumes during Marine Isotope Stage 3 at the Yellow River Delta, China", PLIOMAX Workshop 2016, Talk.
- **T. Pico**, J. Mitrovica, K. Ferrier, J. Braun: "Exploiting sedimentation datasets to model the impact of sediment loading on sea level at the Yellow River Delta", AGU Fall Meeting 2015, Poster presentation.
- T. Pico, J. Mitrovica, K. Ferrier: "Sediment Loading at the Yellow River Delta: Modeling depositional dynamics and impact on regional sea level", GSA Fall Meeting 2015, Talk.
- E. Um, J. Nunes, **T. Pico**, H.A. Stone: "Droplet necklace: Encapsulation of droplets in a microfiber with microfluidics", MRS Spring 2014.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Mentor, Princeton Recognizing Inequalities and Standing for Justice Initiative Summer 2020 Wesley Wiggins '20: "Race in the geosciences: imperialism, scientific racism, and educational training from past to present in the United States"

Harvard Teaching Fellow, Earth and Planetary Sciences

Spring 2019

EPS261: Sea-Level Change. Programming primer, midterm and final project.

Harvard Senior Thesis Adviser, Earth and Planetary Sciences

2018-2019

Rebecca Cleveland Stout '19: "Leveraging Preservation Bias in Last Interglacial Coral Sea-Level Records to Refine Global Ice Volumes Over the Ice Age" ($Hoopes\ Prize\ Winner\ -\ top\ 3\%\ of\ class)$

Harvard WGS98/Junior Indpendent Study Adviser, Women, Gender, and Sexuality Studies 2018-2019

Cynthia Chang '20: 'The Role of Self-Education in Defining Women's Bodies"

Harvard Teaching Fellow, Earth and Planetary Sciences

Fall 2017

EPS10: A Brief History of the Earth. Bi-weekly labs and one-day field trip.

Harvard Independent Study Adviser, Earth and Planetary Sciences

Fall 2017

Sophia Yannis '18: "The influence of the Fennoscandian Ice Sheet on Marine Isotope 6 global ice volume estimates"

Harvard Independent Study Adviser, Earth and Planetary Sciences

Summer 2017

Jaime Weisenberg '20: "Testing MIS 3 Laurentide Ice Sheet configurations"

Harvard Teaching Fellow, Earth and Planetary Sciences

Spring 2017

EPS10: A Brief History of the Earth. Bi-weekly labs and one-day field trip.

Harvard Teaching Fellow, School of Engineering and Applied Sciences

Fall 2015

ES190: Introduction to Material Science. Weekly section.

SCIENTIFIC SERVICE Journal Reviewer: Science Advances, Geology, Climate of the Past, Quaternary Science Reviews, Earth & Planetary Science Letters

Session Organizer and Chair: International Union for Quaternary Science (INQUA) 2019, AGU Fall Meeting 2019, 2020

Scientific Proposal Panelist & Reviewer: NASA, NSF

Leadership,	Mentor, Caltech Women Mentoring Women Program	
MENTORING, AND	IENTORING, AND Action Strategist, Harvard Graduate Women in Science and Engineering Exec Board	
OUTREACH	Mentor, Harvard WiSTEM Mentoring Program (undergraduate group) Invited Speaker, Harvard Graduate Student Union Time's Up Rally Invited Panelist, W.E.B du Bois Society (underrepresented minority group) Invited Speaker, Harvard Foundation Science Conference.	
Invited Speaker, Harvard Natural History Museum Middle School Progra		2017
	Invited Speaker, Harvard Keylatch Summer Program.	2017
	Invited Panelist, Harvard Office of Career Services.	2016
	Leader, Graduate Student/Post-doc Seminar. Weekly department series.	2015-2016
	Non-residential tutor, Leverett (Harvard undergraduate house)	2014-present
	Tutor, Massachussetts Correctional Institute at Framingham,	
	New Jersey Correctional Facilities	2011-2015

Languages English (native), Spanish (bilingual), French (fluent)